<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cloak in its colours; or The Presbyterian unmasked, and proved as dangerous as papists to the Church of England Together with a brief and seasonable ansvver to their late unseasonable queries, and list of the pensioners, humbly offer'd to all true Protestant conformists.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4719B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223880</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896132</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896132</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153867</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79979)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153867)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2384:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cloak in its colours; or The Presbyterian unmasked, and proved as dangerous as papists to the Church of England Together with a brief and seasonable ansvver to their late unseasonable queries, and list of the pensioners, humbly offer'd to all true Protestant conformists.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The second part is a reply to: Sober and seasonable queries humbly offered to all good Protestants in England in order to a choice of the new Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sober and seasonable queries humbly offered to all good Protestants in England in order to a choice of the new Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153867:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Cloak in its Colours; OR THE <hi>Presbyterian Unmasked.</hi> AND Proved as Dangerous as PAPISTS To the CHURCH of ENGLAND. Together with a Brief and Seaſonable ANSWER To their late Unſeaſonable QUERIES, AND <hi>LIST of the Penſioners,</hi> Humbly offer'd to all true PROTESTANT Conformiſts.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets which come to you in Sheeps Cloathing, but inwardly they are Ravening Wolves,</hi> 
               <bibl>Matth. 7.15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for the Author, ANNO DOM. 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153867:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153867:2"/>
            <head>THE Cloak in its Colours; OR, THE <hi>Presbyterians Vnmask'd,</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF ever we wanted Circumſpection or Conduct, if ever we had need of the Spirit of Diſcretion, to diſcern between our feigned Friends and real Well-wiſhers, between undermining Zealots and true Patriots, this muſt be the time; a time, wherein our Religion, our Lives our Liberties, our Eſtates; and, in Fine, our All, lies at ſtake, either to be ſettled and ſecured by our prudent proceedings in this grand Concern; or we to be hopeleſly fool'd of all, by the ſubtilty and guile of our Adverſaries; a time, wherein we are to ſteer our courſe between the two dangerous Gulfs of <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis,</hi> of Popery and Presbytery; and therefore, like wiſe Pilots, muſt carefully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour as well to ſhun the one as avoid the other, leſt at any time it may be ſaid of us,</p>
            <q>Incidit in Scyllam, qui vult vitare Charybdim.</q>
            <p>The experience of ſo many years doth ſufficiently tell us that Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and Papiſts do always deſign the ſubverſion both of our Church and State; and they are both aſſured, that if they could but once ſuppreſs our Religion, they might ſoon advance their own. And therefore wiſe States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do hold it an approved Maxim, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> can never be more ſecure, than when theſe two Sects are kept in even balance, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equally countenanced, or equally ſuppreſs'd.</p>
            <p>I remember to have read in the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtories, how the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Chriſtians of the Primitive Church always held it more dangerous to converſe with Hereticks than with the moſt obſtinate Heathens; their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was, becauſe Heathens were open enemies to the name of Chriſt, and therefore all Chriſtians, from the greateſt Divine to the meaneſt Peaſant, were ſufficiently fore-warned not to believe them; but Hereticks came in Sheeps cloathing, and, under the name of Chriſt, laboured to deſtroy Chriſts Flock: Whence the great Divine. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen, Tract. de Fidei,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nothing is more dangerous than theſe Hereticks, who are upright and Orthodox, in all the reſt; yet by one word, as by a drop of poiſon, do infect the true Faith</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153867:3"/>
            <p>I think we may now with as much reaſon make uſe of this prudent method, as the Primitive Chriſtians have done, and thereupon no leſs, if not more ſuſpect our bigotted Presbyterians, who under the name of Proteſtants, and reformed Chriſtians, do endeavour to deſtroy our Church and State, than the Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Papiſts, who openly profeſs themſelves ſworn enemies to our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. All the Proteſtants of <hi>England</hi> are ſo fully prepoſſeſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with the groſsneſs of Popery, that it's altogether impoſſible they ſhould ever believe ſuch ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Opinions: But the Presbyterians, with their pretended Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, do ſo work, upon the well-meaning and ſhort-ſighted Vulgar, that under the colour of drawing them from Popiſh Superſtitions, they poiſon them unwittingly with Phariſaical hypocriſie. Papiſts do attempt by their private Plots and Conſpiracies to deſtroy our King and Countrey; but the Presbyterians, firſt, by their feign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d pretences of Religion, do rob their King of the hearts of his Subjects, and then diſpoſe of his Life and Kingdom as they pleaſe. The Papiſts did but attempt the former, the Presbyterians have actually done the latter, and, if not timely prevented by the faithful Children of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I am afraid, will endeavour once more to complete their wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>How active and ready they are at preſent with their ſeditious Pamphlets to ſow the ſeed of diſſention between our Gracious King and his Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? nay, they ſcruple not to charge his Sacred Majeſty with corrupting and bribing his Parliament. <hi>Obſtupeſcitecoeli, ſupor hoc,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaketh, <hi>Jex.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Be aſtoniſhed, O ye heavens,</hi> both at the unparallel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d impudence of theſe Miſcreants, and at the extraordinary clemency of our Gracious Sovereign, who ſuffers ſuch Villains to live, and enjoy their liberties, who are not worthy to breath the common air. For if ordinary Robbers deſerve to receive their laſt reward at <hi>Tiburn,</hi> what do they not deſerve who not onely deprive their Fellow-ſubjects of their chiefeſt comfort and earthly happineſs, the gracious ſavour and benevolence of their King; but do alſo 10l their Sovereign of his richeſt Treaſures, and greateſt Strength, the love of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Subjects: For, as the Learned Philoſopher <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num eſt Regi inexpugnabile munimentum, amor civium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All wiſe men have hitherto eſteem'd the Intereſt of Prince and People to be one and the ſame individual Common-weal: And it is a common Maxim in our own Laws, <hi>Theſaurus Regis reſpicit Regem &amp; Regnum.</hi> And again, <hi>Cenſus Regis, eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ima Reipublicae, firmamentum belli, &amp; ornament um pacis; apud Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton, ſect.</hi> 153 <hi>pag.</hi> 106. What ſhall we ſay then of theſe ſactious Spirits, who labour to divide them, and draw a partition between them? Or what reaſon have the blind Zealots to think ſo ill of his Sacred Majeſty? Could they expect a Prince more meek, more juſt, or more loving to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Or, (as the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid) <hi>Whoſe Ox or Aſs has he taken? whom has he defrauded, or whom has he oppreſſed?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.3. If we grumble at his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, like thoſe fooliſh Members in the Fable, who grudged that the Belly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo much of the fruit of their labours, we ſhall at laſt, like them, find the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153867:3"/>
            <p>If our King, the Father of our Countrey, be ſuſpected to ſell us, whom ſhall we truſt to? If God's Repreſentative, and lively Image upon Earth, (whom the All ſeeing Providence has miraculouſly reſtored to heal up the wounds of this bleeding Nation) be thought to betray his Truſt, or that Government, which God committed to his charge; how can we have any aſſurance of our own Repreſentatives fair dealings with us, who theſe many years are Elected, not by prudence or diſcretion, but by favour and Faction, and by people who muſt always ſee double before ever they begin their Election?</p>
            <p>If we doubt of his Majeſties Integrity and Fatherly love towards us, he muſt of neceſſity doubt of our Loyalty towards him; and then, what a Hell it ſhall be for us to live under ſuch a King, and for ſuch a King to rule over us? Are we not much beholding to theſe infernal Emiſſaries, who thus make it their buſineſs to deprive both Prince and People of all worldly felicities; nay, to create unto us a hell upon earth, and draw the whole Kingdom into a <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian</hi> confuſion, that ſo themſelves may fiſh in troubled Waters? If theſe be not the proceedings of the Rump-Parliament, let any man be judge.</p>
            <p>Then, the Presbyterians by their ſpecious hypocriſie perſwaded the Kings Subjects not to comply with his Majeſty in disburſing Money towards the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary expences of the Crown, and alſo the ſecuring and fortifying the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom againſt all Foreign Invaſion; though ſoon after, through the juſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, they were forced to pay <hi>Oliver</hi> at leaſt 60000 pounds a month, and had no thanks for their pains: Now the World knows, how they inſiſt upon the ſame terms, and what the end ſhall be, the Lord alone can tell: but God ſend they be not, for their obſtinacy and perverſneſs to ſo good a King, left by the Divine Providence as a Prey to a Forreign, as then they were to a Domeſtick, Tyrant.</p>
            <p>Then, whoſoever ſtood for the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt thoſe blind Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionaries, was preſently cried down for one Popiſhly inclined, or diſaffected to the Proteſtant Religion, <hi>i. e.</hi> to the <hi>Geneveſian</hi> Goſpel. Now they bring us a Liſt of about 200 Members of the Parliament diſſolved in <hi>January</hi> laſt, as the Kings Penſioners and ſworn Voters, and conſequently no great well-wiſhers of the new Goſpel of <hi>John,</hi> and his onely compleat Reformation, warning us to chooſe no ſuch perſons again, becauſe (like the Church of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea, Revel.</hi> 3.15.) <hi>they are neither hot nor cold,</hi> neither Popiſh nor Reformed, as <hi>Alexander Henderſon,</hi> a notorious Presbyterian, diſputing againſt our Royal Martyr, ſcrupled not to ſay of the whole Church of <hi>England</hi> (in the Book intituled, <hi>Reliquiae Carolinae, part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 329.) And ſurely, we have reaſon enough not to chooſe theſe Gentlemen for our Repreſentatives in Parliament, ſince they are no Presbyterians, and conſequently no true Proteſtants, which, in our new found Logick now in faſhion, muſt be <hi>Synomyns,</hi> or <hi>Termini conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibiles. O tempor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>! O mores!</hi> Bloody Presbyterians muſt be entruſted with our Religion, Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates, and true-hearted Proteſtants exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and rejected. Theſe 200 perſons, becauſe no Presbyterians, muſt be laid aſide, notwithſtanding their eminent ſervices both to the King and Kingdom for many years together in the late Parliament, which are ſo numerous, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deſerve ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>rick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in praiſe both of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153867:4"/>their Loyalty to their King, and fidelity to their Countrey: Yet nevertheleſs we muſt uſe them now (ſo <hi>John's</hi> new Goſpel commands us) as the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> uſed their Leading-men and greateſt Hero's, who moſt obliged them, and beſt defended their Countrey; for which they were paid with hatred, and rewarded with ingratitude; nay, often perſecuted, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying that Countrey, which ſeveral times they had ſaved from apparent ruine and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But awake, my beloved Patriots, and as you tender the welfare of your loving Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> caſt off this unſeaſonable ſlumber, rub your eyes and look about you; let us make it our buſineſs to ſecure in time our Church and State againſt thoſe undermining Engineers, and, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Dum tempus habemus, operemur bonum, Gal.</hi> 6.10. Let us make choice of thoſe worthy perſons, who by their ſingular conſtancy in maintaining the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt all Fanatical Oppoſers, became thus formidable to theſe Phariſaical Incendiaries of our Countrey; ſurely we cannot but have reaſon enough to love them, ſince the Presbyterians do ſo vehemently hate them. Let us uſe all poſſible endeavours, that as Papiſts ſo Presbyterians, and all Non-conformiſts, may be for ever excluded from ſitting in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and let not their ſpecious hypocriſie, or plauſible pretences of abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing Popiſh Superſtitions, or maintaining the Proteſtant Religion, work upon our credulity to countenance their contrivances, or encourage them in the pernicious deſigns.</p>
            <p>Now they will tell us how ready they are to combine with the Church of <hi>England</hi> to pull down Popery, and that Scarlet Whore of <hi>Babylon;</hi> but you muſt withall give them leave to root out all Popiſh Reliques and Rubbiſh; and then good Biſhops, look to your ſelves, your Gowns and Surplices. You were lately like to be brought upon the Stage, not onely as burthenſome to the Nation, but alſo as Popiſhly inclin'd, nay, countenancing the horrid Plot of the Papiſts: And had not his Sacred Majeſty, like his glorious Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpos'd himſelf, and ſtood your Shield, you might ere now moſt truly have ſaid, <hi>Fuimus Troes.</hi> But if the Shepherds be thus threatned by theſe ravenous Wolves, what kind uſage can the Flock expect at their hands? Yet as for my own particular I muſt confeſs, I cannot handſomely excuſe our Shepherds themſelves, or their unſeaſonable careleſneſs in this deſperate juncture of Affairs, for bearing in a great proportion the blame of all thoſe dangers, which are now apparently eminent both to themſelves and their Flocks together, when I conſider how plainly they ſee with what pernicious contrivances the whole Church is menac'd by the fiery Presbyterians, and yet they are ſo ſilent, nay, ſo dumb, (like thoſe who by the Prophet are called, <hi>canes muti, non valentes latrare, Iſa.</hi> 56.10.) yet they dare not mutter againſt them, nor make the People ſenſible how to prevent their wicked deſigns, as eaſily they might, if in their Sermons and Exhortations they would take ſo much pains, as to perſwade their Auditors to make choice of ſuch and ſuch ſelect perſons, whom th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ant and exact in obſerving the Rites and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and withall, zealous to propagate her
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153867:4"/>Doctrines, and able and reſolute to maintain it. Had this, I ſay, been duely performed, we might ſoon aſſure our ſelves of a firm ſettlement both of Church and State, and never apprehend any danger from thoſe Fanatical Sectaries, who, like <hi>Samſon</hi>'s Foxes, are tied together by the tail of Sedition, (though otherwiſe divided) to burn and deſtroy our whole Harveſt.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe they will tell us further, they onely differ from the Church of <hi>England</hi> in ſome leſſer points, and ſmall Ceremonies; but (to omit, that hereby they acknowledge themſelves wicked Schiſmaticks, who upon ſo trivial a cauſe have departed from the Mother Church believe me, had they but the upper hand, be the differences never ſo ſmall, adieu to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the Rump-Parliament has ſufficiently informed us</p>
            <p>Wherefore, my beloved Church-men and Countrey-men, ſuffer not your ſelves to be gull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by theſe blind excuſes or frivolous pretences; and do but ſeriouſly examine in your own judgments, with what colour of truth can theſe ſuper-ſanctified Hypocrites affirm, that they differ onely in ſuch ſmall punctilio's from the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Or are they very Fundamentals of our Government ſuch trivial matters in their Goſpel? It's evident, I ſuppoſe, to all the world, that Papiſts were never perſecuted in this Kingdom for any Scholaſtical niceties, or ſpeculative ſubtilties of Chriſtian Religion, but were always abhorr'd, and held unworthy of all humane Society for their pernicious Tenets concerning the Power and Authority of Secular Princes? But what, if I do here briefly demonſtrate, that the Presbyterians common doctrine and practiſe is altogether as pernicious, if not far more deſtructive, to Monarchical Government, than the moſt deſperate principles of the Papiſts; will not you then more carefully look about you, and hereafter be more cautious how you deal with ſuch ſubtil underminers of our Church and State?</p>
            <p>To give you therefore full ſatisfaction concerning the Presbyterians unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Loyalty, I ſhall trace down the current of their Goſpel from the very ſource and original of its being, and will begin with their ſuper illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated Patriarch, the famous <hi>Calvin,</hi> ſometimes Pope of <hi>Geneva,</hi> who was inſpired by the Spirit (you know whom) thus to ſpeak of Temporal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns, <hi>Earthly Princes do deprive themſelves of all Power when they oppoſe God; nay, they are not worthy to be held in the number of men: we must therefore ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpit in their faces than obey them.</hi> In <hi>Dan. c.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 22, 25. Neither is his worthy Darling, Dr. <hi>Beza,</hi> any thing behind in this point, of whom, Mr. <hi>Sutt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe,</hi> in his Anſwer to a certain Libel Supplicatory, thus ſpeaketh; <hi>Beza, in his Book,</hi> De Jure Magiſtratus, <hi>doth arm the Subject againſt the Prince, and, in effect, overthroweth the Authority of Chriſtian Kings and Magistrates</hi>— <hi>Suttcliffe (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oco ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.)</hi> writes in theſe words: <hi>Noble-men</hi> (ſaith <hi>Knox</hi>) <hi>ought to reform Religion, if the King will not: If the Prince will not yield to his Nobles and People, he armeth them with power to depoſe him. Nay,</hi> (ſaith he further) <hi>if Princes be Tyrants against God and his truth, their Subjects are freed from their Oathes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obedience.</hi> With him accordeth <hi>Buchanan,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>The People is more excellent than the King, and hath right to bestow the Crown at pleaſure: That
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153867:5"/>the People may arraign the King: That albeit St.</hi> Paul <hi>commanded obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Tyrants, yet it was in reſpect of the times, and the people that were weak, and not able to take arms.</hi> And Dr. <hi>Bancroft,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in his Book of <hi>Dangerous Poſitions,</hi> gives this general Cenſure of them all. <hi>Such Divinity as this, is not holden by</hi> Knox <hi>and</hi> Buchanan <hi>alone, but generally, for ought I can perceive, by the chief Conſiſtorians beyond the Seas.</hi> He means <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, Beza,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Geneveſian Sanhedrim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let any man be judge, how well theſe Goſpellary principles of our Presbyterians agree with the practiſe and Doctrine of the holy Apoſtles, who (as Dr. <hi>Bilſon,</hi> in his <hi>Chriſtian Subject,</hi> faith) <hi>obey'd Tyrants, that commanded all things againſt Religion: And in thoſe thing that were commanded againſt God, they did ſubmit themſelves with meekneſs to endure the Magiſtrates pleaſure but not to obey his will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we need not much admire, that they differ ſo much from the bleſſed Apoſtles, when we find the dregs of Chriſtians, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>apiſts themſelves, in great number ſo far beyond them in teaching Allegiance and Fidelity to Secular Princes, that as far as Proteſtants are beyond Papiſts in this particular, ſo far are many Papiſts beyond the bigotted Presbyterians: <hi>Subjects</hi> (ſay the <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi> in <hi>Rom. c,</hi> 13.) <hi>are bound in temporal things to obey even the Heathen, being their lawful Kings, and to be ſubject to them for conſcience, to obſerve their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Laws, to pay them Tribute, to pray for them, and to perform all other Duties of natural Allegiance.</hi> Nay, ſo far were many Papiſts from holding this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Goſpel of <hi>Knox</hi> and his <hi>Boutefous,</hi> that they declared it abſolutely er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous and Heretical in any Chriſtian to believe it, as appeareth by their Council of <hi>Constance, Seſſ.</hi> 15. in theſe words, <hi>The holy Synod has been lately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that certain erroneous Opinions were held, contrary to the peace and welfare of the Common-wealth,</hi> viz. <hi>That a Tyrant may be lawfully and meritoriouſly taken away and killed by any Subject or Vaſſal of his, notwithſtanding any Oath of Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or Allegiance that he had made to him. Such Doctrine</hi> (ſaith the Council) <hi>is contrary both to Faith and Manners; and whoſoever ſhall hold it obſtinately, are Hereticks, and as ſuch to be proceeded againſt according to the Canons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now do but compare this Decree of a Popiſh Council, to that Diabolical expreſſion of <hi>Knox,</hi> (that <hi>Delphian</hi> Oracle of the Presbyterian <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) in his <hi>Hiſtory of Scotland, page</hi> 372. where he declares, <hi>That he could be content, that there were publick rewards appointed for ſuch Aſſaſſinates and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of Tyrants, as there are for ſuch as kill Wolves.</hi> And then I leave it to your Conſcience to judge, whether the Presbyterians be not the worſt Subjects that ever own'd the name of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But let us proceed a little further, and ſee what worthy fruit has this holy Goſpel of theirs produced theſe hundred years paſt in this Iſland of great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and we ſhall find it very true <hi>Non poteſt arbor mala bonos fructus facere, Matth.</hi> 7.18. Nay, we ſhall find, that the Papiſts themſelves, ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Reformation in this Iſland; were never convicted of half ſuch wicked and diabolical practiſes againſt their Prince, as the Presbyterians have undeniably committed againſt their undoubted Sovereign. 'Tis true, many
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153867:5"/>wicked Papiſts, by their Plots and Conſpiracies, have often attempted, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt inhumane manner, to deſtroy our King, and ſubvert our Government: But the brave Presbyterians, ſcorning to truſt always to ſuch pitiful contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances under-hand, have at ſeveral times publickly raiſed whole Armies in open Rebellion againſt their Prince and have not onely attempted, but actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally compleated the deſtruction of Kings and Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>I do not wonder indeed, how cruelly they dealt with our preſent Sovereigns Great Grand-mother, Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (a profeſs'd Papiſt) in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning and baniſhing her the Kingdom, and allowing her no liberty of exerciſing her Religion either in private or publick; of which unworthy uſage, King <hi>James,</hi> of glorious memory, ſpeaking of thoſe Puritan Hypocrites, complaineth in theſe words, <hi>How they uſed that poor Lady, my Mother, is not unknown, and with grief I may remember it, who deſired onely a private Chappel, wherein to ſerve God after her manner with ſome ſelected perſons, but could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it at their hands.</hi> In the ſum of the Conference before his Majeſty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Biſhops and others of the Clergy, <hi>Anno</hi> 1604. <hi>page</hi> 81. I wonder not, I ſay, at theſe inhumane dealings againſt a Papiſt, when we have ſo late an example of their unparallel'd cruelty, in the Tragical and never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten murder, not onely of a Proteſtant Prince, but alſo of the moſt meek, the moſt juſt, and the moſt Religious of Princes, King <hi>Charles</hi> the I. and this diſmal Tragedy perpetrated, not by any private Deſperado's of that Faction, as Popiſh contrivances for the moſt part have been; but by the general Vote and conſent of all; and perpetrated, not by any ſecret contrivances, but (which mainly aggravates the crime, if poſſible) by a publick formality of Juſtice, and pretence of ſecuring the true Faith and Worſhip of God. <hi>For ſince it is manifeſt,</hi> (as the <hi>Roman</hi> Orator well obſerved) <hi>that of all injuſtice, none is more odious and abominable, than where men act their Villanies under a vizard and pretence of good;</hi> what crime can be more diabolical, than for Subjects to Arraign their Sovereign, and the beſt of Kings, as a Tyrant, ſubverting the Government and true Proteſtant Religion; and under theſe ſpecious pretences, and that Uſurped Title, <hi>God with us,</hi> not onely Sacrifice his Sacred Perſon to their Fury, but alſo (to multiply their Villany) endeavour to deſtroy his Fame and Reputation for ever.</p>
            <p>And though this execrable and unparallel'd Murder has been unexpectedly pardon'd, through the exceſſive clemency of our preſent Sovereign, which graciouſly extended it ſelf, not onely to the ſeduced Multitude, but even to the ſparing the unworthy lives of ſome of the grand <hi>Pilates</hi> themſelves; yet ſo far is this favour from working its due effects upon theſe ungrateful Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants, that, like Spiders, which ſuck poiſon out of the fineſt Flowers, they grow daily worſe by his Majeſty's gracious condeſcenſions to them, always watching an opportunity, either by ſecret Contrivances and Conſpiracies, to ſubvert the Government, as the Fanatical Rabble of <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s Adherents in <hi>Ireland</hi> conſpired in the year 1665 to murder his Majeſties Lord Lieutenant there, and ſurprize his Caſtle and City of <hi>Dublin;</hi> or to draw whole Armies into the Field in open Rebellion againſt his Majeſty, as they have lately done
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153867:6"/>in <hi>Scotland,</hi> not onely in the year 1677, but alſo this laſt Summer, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon the Proroguing the Parliament here: And to have their God propitious to their holy deſigns, they zealouſly conſecrated their Goſpellary Rebellion with the moſt inhumane Butchery of the Right Reverend Father in God, the Primate of that Kingdom; and withall moſt arrogantly burnt his Majeſties Laws and Statutes in the publick place of Execution.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding all theſe inſufferable indignities, we ſee the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, both here and there, are ſtill in vogue, and in good hopes too, by their expected Intereſt in the next Parliament, ere long to lay a ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for the <hi>Geneveſian</hi> Goſpel in theſe three Kingdoms, and refine our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Reformation, and purge it from all thoſe heaps of Popiſh Rubbiſh and Superſtitions, which their Patriarch <hi>Calvin,</hi> (<hi>Ep.</hi> 26.) affirms are ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Church of <hi>England:</hi> We ſee, the intended Conſpiracies of others is daily exaggerated by the Pens of Learned Men; but the Presbyterians open Treacheries ſeal'd with the deepeſt ſilence. And it's very remarkable, how the late horrid Plot was no ſooner diſcovered in <hi>London,</hi> but all the Papiſts of theſe three Kingdom were preſently under a Cloud, and, as it were, ſtruck with a ſudden damp, and bereaved of all vital motions: But the Presbyterians actual Rebellion in <hi>Scotland,</hi> (and that for Religion too, as appears by their Declarations) was ſo far from daunting the reſt of that Faction here, that they writ out ſeveral Pamphlets to extenuate their Brethren's wickedneſs, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe their Inſurrection.</p>
            <p>But certainly, had the Papiſts of this Kingdom been as evidently proved guilty of Juſtice <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s Murder, as the Presbyterians of <hi>Seotland</hi> have been undeniably criminal of the Biſhop of St. <hi>Andrew</hi>'s bloody Tragedy; or could the former be as unqueſtionably proved to have conſpired his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's death, or the ſubverſion of the Government, as the latter have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly deſigned both, in their late execrable Rebellion, as appeareth by their Declarations, wherein, Puritan-like, they ſcruple not to charge his Sacred Majeſty with perjury, and violation of the Covenant, together with ſeveral other Presbyterian expreſſions; and beſides, their very Inſurrection maketh it undeniable: For (as Dr. <hi>Bilſon, loco ſupra cit.</hi> well obſerveth) <hi>He that may fight, may kill; and war againſt the Prince, and killing the Prince, are of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence inevitable.</hi> Could theſe things, I ſay, be thus indiſputably proved againſt the Papiſts, ſurely all Proteſtants wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d unanimouſly riſe againſt ſuch bloody Tygers, and quite extirpate them root and branch out of this Iſland for ever. How ſtrangely then comes it to paſs, that Papiſts are ſo unfortunate in their wickedneſs. as ſtill to be exclaimed againſt for crimes, in the judgment of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe and judicious men, not yet unexceptionably proved againſt them, and the Presbyterians undeniable wickedneſs preſently buried in oblivion?</p>
            <p>Believe me, Sirs, the caſe is of a very dangerous conſequence, and it prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks no good to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> it plainly ſheweth, how the diſſembling Hypocrites, by their plauſible pretences, have gained the hearts of the ſeduced people. And we may be fully perſwaded, they could never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to write ſuch ſeditious Pamphlets, and preſume to charge,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153867:6"/>not onely the chief Biſhop, but alſo the whole Church of <hi>England,</hi> with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Doctrine, and withall endeavour to juſtifie their own Schiſmatical ſeparation from her Communion, as plainly they do in ſeveral Libels, and particularly in one, by them called, <hi>The Countrey's Vindication,</hi> had they not been ſure of a ſtrong party to ſecond their attempts, and juſtifie their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore beware in time, and take heed, leſt while we are intentive to drive away the Wolf from our Flock, the Fox may come in and deſtroy our Vineyard. Fourty years are not yet expired, ſince we were forced to make uſe even of the Papiſts themſelves, to defend our King and Countrey from the Rebellious Presbyterians; God ſend we be not again, through our ſtupid care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs, reduced to that extremity.</p>
            <p>We ſee how continually active the reſtleſs Spirits are, and what cunning ſtratagems they uſe, to ſow the ſeed of jealouſie and diviſion between the moſt true-hearted Children of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and how whomſoever they find couragious and reſolute in maintaining the Rights of the Church, and Prerogatives of the Crown, preſently (as in the Long Parliament) they exclaim againſt him, as one of the King's evil Counſellors, or as a down-right Papiſt, or at leaſt Popiſhly inclin'd.</p>
            <p>They bring us four and twenty <hi>Quaeries,</hi> or ſo many Impertinencies, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the choice of a new Parliament; new indeed, becauſe, if poſſible, it muſt wholly conſiſt of Presbyterians, and other Fanatical Sectaries, which, but in the Rump-parliaments time, was never ſeen in <hi>England.</hi> In moſt of theſe Queries, they tell us of the Papiſts cruelty, I wiſh they had joyn'd the Presbyterians too, for <hi>England</hi> has ſufficiently taſted of the bloody con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances of both parties. If the Monument at <hi>London-bridge</hi> be a <hi>Memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> of the Papiſts fiery Zeal, what does <hi>Charing-croſs</hi> ſpeak of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians bloody devotion? We know full well which of the later have been either Actors or Abettors in murdering our King, but we could never certainly find which of the former has been concerned in firing our City: Yet the buſie Spirits muſt cry Whore firſt, and by thus crying ſo loud againſt the horrid Treacheries of the Papiſts, they think to divert our eyes from diſcerning their own pernicious deſigns.</p>
            <p>But we would gladly give them leave to ſpit their venom againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and rail at them with all virulent invectives imaginable, had themſelves been ſo Loyal in their actions, as not to ſurpaſs them in wickedneſs; or ſo dutiful in their expreſſions, as not to ſnarl at his Sacred Majeſty, nor with ſuch arrogance openly cenſure his Princely wiſdom, in proroguing and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving his Parliaments, as if he deſign'd to encourage the Plotters to murder himſelf, as though, forſooth, the blood-thirſty Presbyterians ſhould wiſh his Majeſty better than himſelf can do; whereas it's apparent to the World, their main deſign is to tread the foot-ſteps of their Fathers, and raiſe again the <hi>Cromwellian</hi> Goſpel and Government.</p>
            <p>To this end, the <hi>Oliverian</hi> Presbyterians of <hi>Ireland,</hi> having ill ſpent what they have worſe acquired in that Kingdom, do daily flock over hither in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153867:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>whole Swarms, and under the colour of this late Popiſh Plot, do leave no ſtone unremoved to bring that Nation again into inteſtine troubles, thereby to leave that remnant of true Proteſtants, which God has miraculoufly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in that Kingdom, to the mercileſs mercy either of the cruel Papiſts, or bloody Fanaticks: Nay, they make it their buſineſs to blow the Bellows of Rebellion here, as lately they have done in <hi>Scotland,</hi> though, by God's provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to their own utter confuſion.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore, dear Countrey-men, beware in time of theſe hypocritical Religionaries, and as we tender the peace and welfare, nay, the very being of our beloved Mother, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> let us uſe all our endeavours in this our choice of a new Parliament, that no Presbyterian, Papiſt, or other Fanatick, be ever admitted to ſit in that Honourable Houſe. Let us not be ſo credulous as to believe, that Schiſmatical Sectaries, who daily undervalue the Laws of the Church, will ever endeavour to make Laws to eſtabliſh the Church: We may as well believe, that Wolves will make Folds to preſerve the Flock from ravenous Beaſts, as that Presbyterians or other Fanaticks will ever paſs any Laws for ſecuring either Church or State againſt their own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining contrivances. I think the abomination of deſolation, which through your unlucky Election of treacherous Presbyterians for your Repreſentatives in Parliament, happened to the amazement of the World in the Year (48) ſpeaks loud enough to diſſwade you from ſuch deſperate choice for the future. Be wiſe therefore now, and circumſpective, and while by one days prudent choice of faithful and true-hearted Repreſentatives, you can ſecure your Lives and Liberties, and prevent all eminent dangers which threaten <hi>our</hi> Church and State, make uſe of ſo fair an opportunity: Believe me, if you let it ſlip, you may for ever lament, but never be able to redreſs your loſſes. Remember the old ſaying, <hi>Poſt eſt occaſio calva.</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Principiis obſta: ſero medicina paratur,</l>
                  <l>Cummala per longas invaluere moras.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
